okay so today what I want to do is talk
about a what I think is actually a very
very deep concept that I learned about
in a book called the secret of our
success by Joseph Henrich and I'll put
some links to the book down below and
he's actually got a number of really
good talks on YouTube so I'll put a link
to a couple of those videos as well the
concept here is the distinction between
dominance and prestige and the role of
that distinction plays in culture and
cultural revolution okay so the idea
here begins with the insight that human
beings have very few hardwired instincts
unlike most of other animals which are
born reasonably well capable of quickly
becoming functional human beings as we
know important pretty helpless and one
of the very few instincts that were able
to consistently find that seems to be
hardwired really as far back as we've
been able to look so far even like one
or two months as far as I know is a very
very interesting and unique
characteristic in humans and that is
that from a very early age human beings
are very hard wired to endeavor to
identify who they should pay attention
to and they do it by figuring out or
identifying who everybody else is paying
attention to when I suppose in idea of
social attention allocation so you
imagine a two-month-old even a
two-month-old will be scanning the
environment to identify who in that
environment is worth paying attention to
and then will endeavor to anyway
whatever they can grasp of what's going
on over there particularly or start
intimidating behaviors with the
expectation or the hope that some of
those behaviors might in fact be the
ones that are why they're the subject of
social attention and therefore worth
emulating and so it's a kind of a crude
tool for collectively figuring out what
are the right kinds of things to do but
I guess the point is that so far as we
can tell it seems to be the thing the
key that enabled Homo sapiens to develop
culture now there's a whole bunch of
stuff we could do on just that but what
I want
about is the the two different kinds of
social hierarchies that emerged in this
context so the first kind of social
hierarchy is is relatively commonly
discussed these days and browns of
people understood and that is a
dominance hierarchy that's the idea here
and all social animals have this
particular structure particularly among
males where the ability to engage in
effective use of physical strength
allows a particular male to achieve
dominance of other males and then
Authority in the social structure that
cascades down in some sort of
hierarchical element that's a very
coarse brush of the of the concept I
don't want to spend a whole lot of time
there as I said it's it's not that hard
to grasp these days the important part
is the the other kind of hierarchy
because as far as as we can tell are
these as far as I know who based on the
formations that I've been exposed to
this particular hierarchical approach is
unique among humans and is very
distinctly associated with the fact that
we're a cultural animal and Henry calls
this the the prestige hierarchy and so
what happens to this in the prestige
hierarchy is this is dynamic especially
with this hardwired habit which is those
individual members of the group who are
most attended to by the other members of
the group therefore end up on the top of
the prestige hierarchy and have a social
status that is comparable to not
necessarily the same as the comparable
to individuals who at the top of the
dominance hierarchy so humans as a
tribal obligate pack animal have two
distinct hierarchies that are happening
simultaneously and a large part of the
complexity of our social environment are
in fact based upon that tension that on
the one hand we are at a deep man
million level attuned to dominance
displays and dominance hierarchies and
trying to figure out where we live in
that picking order but at the same time
at a human level we are constantly
seeking to find out who we should be
paying attention to and
should be emulating along the prestige
hierarchy now notice the distinct ways
that one goes about navigating this
heart is and how the heart is play out
so we just did one example
Hendrix example and that has to do with
the relationship between dominant and
non-dominant males and high prestige and
non high prestige males in the two
hierarchies so in a dominance hierarchy
non dominant males really quite
distinctly want to go out of their way
making the acquaintance with the
dominant male you don't want to get his
attempt you don't want to make eye
contact you avoid it at all costs
because that will be perceived as a
dominance challenge and then you
consequently involve some sort of
dominance conflict which by hypothesis
here you'll lose now of course in that
context there's not a whole lot of
learning that can take place right it's
very difficult to learn from someone if
you can't even make eye contact with
them if you're trying to avoid proximity
to them by contrast in the prestige
hierarchy the whole point is in fact
connection and communication so the the
low prestige males are consistently
seeking who they should be attending to
and then endeavouring to find ways to
cultivate an opportunity to be in the
proximity of hyper Steve males so that
they can have an opportunity to emulate
whatever it is the causes them to be
high prestige I'm so if you if a
particular male happens to be notably
good at chipping hand axes and that is
getting him a lot of attention then as a
young male you see that attention you
you're glued to him and you get near by
him and try to figure out how to how to
absorb this knowledge and of course that
Ben enables transfer of knowledge to
occur and then transfer of knowledge
enables the development and propagation
of culture but the last part is the most
important part and that is in fact the
relationship of the high prestige male
to the rest of the prestige hierarchy
because if the high prestige male
behaves in the same way that the hot the
dominant male behaves it'll break down
the dynamic so the high prestige male
has to allow in fact
pacifically benefit from the lack of
conflict and the presence of the other
males who are endeavoring to
emulate his skills so the high prestige
mail far from optimizing for and tuning
for dominance optimizes in Tunes for
teaching and for skillfully separating
those individual mails who in fact be to
his benefit to interact with and to
increase his capacity to be successful
in a mating resource generation and just
staying a lot you know who's good to be
on his team and so in as if happening is
that the the skill set of the high
prestige mail is in what we might call
ethical leadership or in in teaching
which is a far cry from the skill set of
the dominance mail and of course I'm I'm
articulating this all in the mail
framework there are various horrible
relationships and the female framework
and then in mixed mechanisms as well for
sure but the the male hierarchies are a
bit easier to grasp as a single example
so so to recap human beings seem to be
uniquely distinguished in evolution from
other primates from another hominids
from other mammals in that we have been
hardwired in a very deep way and
singularly for this notion of attention
of social attention and of emulation
this is related to connected to the
emergence of a completely separate
social hierarchical framework around
prestige prestige and dominance run
simultaneously in Homo sapiens and the
tension between prestige and dominance
is quite significant in understanding
the complexity of human social
relationships I guess the last note
since done this pretty quickly is to say
that if you imagine the kinds of social
dynamics that are associated with the
effective control of rival risk
resources you'll notice that dominance
is actually a pretty good approach you
know
what I want to do is control a watering
hole the dominance is is the approach
they don't take whereas if the endeavor
is to generate antivirus resources then
postage is the right approach to take
and so it may be in fact that this
distinction between rival risk and anti
rather as' is directly related now this
is a proposition that I'd put out there
to consider to the distinction between
the dominance and the prestige
approaches and that I would go further
and proposed it is precisely the
selection gradient associated with the
ability to grasp and advance along the
anti rivals frontier that gave rise to
the niche of prestige and that we now
are in a co-evolutionary dynamic between
the prestige gradient to the prestige
selection gradient and the antivirus
Misha all right ten minutes that's all I
hope it's useful